Finding Aid for Dept. of Astronomy (University of Michigan) records, 1960-1989 (bulk 1980-1989)
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Astronomy (University of Michigan) records 1960-1989 1980-1989
University of Michigan. Dept. of Astronomy.
2 linear ft.
91457 Bimu C26/2
The Dept. of Astronomy records contain the records of the Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy (AURA) observatories visiting committee, 1980-1985; the chairman’s daily file for William A. Hiltner and Robert P. Kirshner / Douglas Richstone, 1960-1988; and various subject files.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group was transferred from the Department of Astronomy (Donor # 7849, no longer in use, and # 1465 ) on August 14, 1990. Other additions have been received
The record group is open for use without restriction.
The first mention of the Department of Astronomy as a unit of the University of Michigan was in 1929 when Will Carly Rufus was named Acting Director of the Observatories and acting Chairman of the Department of Astronomy. It is surmised that the Department was created in that year. During the 1980's, Chairmen of the Department included Robert P. Kirshner and Douglas O. Richstone.
Historically, the Department has operated, established, and cooperatively maintained a number of astronomical observatories. The Detroit Observatory was built in Ann Arbor in 1854. The Lamont-Hussey Observatory in Bloemfontein, South Africa was dedicated in 1928. In 1972, the Lamont-Hussey Observatory was closed and its equipment and records were returned to Ann Arbor. The McMath-Hulbert Observatory was opened in 1930 in Lake Angelus, Michigan and the McGraw-Hill Observatory in Arizona, which featured a 1.3 meter telescope, was opened in 1975.
One of the department's accomplishments was its participation in the creation of the Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy (AURA). In 1957, Robert R. McMath of the University of Michigan became Chairman of the Board of Directors of AURA Inc. Three observatories are under the group's charge; Kitt Peak National Observatory in Arizona, the Cerro Tololo Inter-American Observatory in Chile, and the Sacramento Peak Observatory in Sunspot, New Mexico. On November 2, 1962, AURA acknowledged Dr. McMath's contributions to the organization by naming the world's largest solar telescope located on Kitt Peak in his honor.
A detailed history of the Department of Astronomy at the University of Michigan and its related observatories is available in The University of Michigan: An Encyclopedic Survey.
The records of the Department of Astronomy at the University of Michigan document the internal workings of the department, its relationship with the University and the scholarly community, and issues relating to the observatories under the direction of the Department, particularly in the 1970s and 1980s. The records have been divided into three series: Chairman's Files; Departmental Topical Files; and Appeals Complaints Committee.
Subjects:
Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy.; Astronomical observatories.; Astronomy--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Astronomy.; University of Michigan. Observatory.
- Chairman's File
  The Chairman's File series is divided into two subseries. There is a small subseries of departmental records from the period when William A. Hiltner was chairman. There is also a subseries of files relating to the internal and external workings of the Department under Robert P. Kirshner and, later, Douglas O. Richstone in the 1980's. Arranged in reverse chronological order, this subseries includes incoming and outgoing memoranda and correspondence which discuss faculty and doctoral appointments, fund-raising activities, and recommendations.
  - William A. Hiltner files
    - Budget, 1960-1973 (Box 1)
    - Departmental Review Committee, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Departmental Review Committee, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - Faculty appointments, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Faculty minutes, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Programs, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Undergraduate astronomy center, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Robert P. Kirshner / Douglas Richstone daily file
    - 1984, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1985, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1987, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1988, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Departmental Topical Files
  The Departmental Topical Files series is made up of correspondence, memoranda, and grant and research proposals. The series is arranged alphabetically by subject and within folders, there is a rough chronological arrangement. It is diverse, containing materials on observatories, the Department's communication with the University Provost, a Historic Instruments Preservation Project, and the dedication of the William A. Hiltner Telescope. Most of the materials are from the 1980's. Since the Department's faculty members have often been involved in the Association for University Research in Astronomy (AURA), there are also records in the collection which document that organization.
  - American Astronomical Society Meeting, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - AURA Observatories Visiting Committee, 1980-1985, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - AURA Observatories Visiting Committee, 1980-1985, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Dean's Office: Observatory Problems, Lamont Trust, Reallocation, 1962-1969 (Box 2)
  - Dedication of William A Hiltner Telescope, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Kitt Peak National Observatory Equipment (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence Regarding Sale of McMath Observatory Equipment, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Provost, 1985-1987 (Box 2)
  - Radio Astronomy Observatory, University of Michigan, Radio Review, 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Steneck, Nicholas H.: Historic Instruments Observatory Preservation Project, 1987 (Box 2)
- Complaint Appeal Committee
  The Complaint Appeal Committee series contains documentation relating to the Anne Cowley case requesting her promised faculty appointment with the Dept. of Astronomy.
  - Anne Cowley case, 1966-1974 (Box 2)
    (includes files transferred to department chairman Hiltner by James B. Griffin)
Related Materials
For additional records relating to the Department of Astronomy and the observatories, the researcher is advised to consult the record group University of Michigan Observatory.